Most traders don't actually understand
how the markets they're trading in work.
In most serious professions, you'd
expect somebody to understand the basic
mechanics of the thing they're doing.
But in trading, loads of people are
risking real money in a market that they
couldn't explain properly if you stopped
and asked them one simple question. What
actually causes price to move? What you
usually get instead is a bunch of
buzzwords like supply and demand,
liquidity, institutions, smart money,
manipulation, order flow. People hear
these phrases often enough that it
starts to feel like they actually
understand the thing, but it's a
textbook example of the illusion of
explanatory depth. They can throw the
words around, but they can't tell you
exactly how it works. And that's a bit
of a problem because if you don't have a
deep enough understanding of how the
market actually works, you'll naturally
end up relying on illogical trading
approaches with no way of really telling
whether what you're doing is valid or
not. And that's how people end up
following these so-called strategies
that sound legit but are no better than
just flipping a coin and hoping for the
best. So, in this video, we're going to
build the proper foundations. You're
going to learn how markets actually
work, what causes price movements to
happen and the components that drive
that, the role of key participants like
market makers and institutional traders,
and how all of this changes the kind of
opportunities you can start spotting in
the markets. So, by the end of the
video, you should be able to look at the
price movements you see on the chart and
think about them in a much more
practical and much deeper way and
therefore get better at reading context,
which is really the doorway to actually
finding real positive expectancy
opportunities. Because once you
understand the basic mechanics of
markets, you'll already be miles ahead
of most other traders who are still
mumbling things about supply and demand
without being able to explain a bloody
thing. Now, in case you're watching this
channel for the first time, I'm
Nicholas. I started learning to trade
around 2002, so almost 25 years ago now.
And I've been obsessed with the markets
ever since. I left my career in banking
to become a full-time trader in 2012.
And so trading has been my life ever
since then. And if you want to learn how
I actually trade, there's a link to a
free training series in the description.
But if you ask me what's the single most
foundational thing that every serious
trader really should understand, it's
exactly what we're going to go through
in this video. So let's get into it.
Let's start with the obvious question.
What is a market? Well, at the most
basic level, a market is a place where
buyers and sellers can trade with each
other. So the market's job is to
facilitate exchange. And in financial
markets, that job has two main parts.
Providing liquidity and helping with
price discovery. So liquidity is
basically the ease at which an asset can
be conversed into cash without
significantly affecting its price. And
price discovery is the process of
figuring out what price the asset can
actually transact at right now. So if
you bring everyone into one market into
one exchange, you make both those jobs
much easier. Now most of the financial
markets that traders tend to focus on
operate as a continuous double auction.
And that term sounds a bit more
complicated than it actually is. It just
means that buyers are continuously
submitting orders at prices they're
willing to pay and sellers are
continuously submitting orders at prices
they're willing to sell for and the
market is constantly trying to match
those intentions into actual trades. So
it's a bit like a very fast very
organized version of a market stall
where people are constantly calling out
what they'll pay and what they'll accept
except instead of shouting the exchange
is matching orders electronically
according to a rule book. It's
continuous because the process keeps
running while the market's open. It's
double auction because both sides are
active at the same time. Buyers are
competing with other buyers, sellers are
competing with other sellers, and the
market just keeps moving to where trade
can actually take place. Now, the exact
plumbing of all of this can differ
across markets. So, different exchanges
might have different matching rules,
different tick sizes, different opening
and closing procedures, different levels
of transparency. For example, futures
markets operate slightly differently
between each other and they all differ
from spot forex which is decentralized.
But always the core logic is the same.
Orders come in, those orders interact
according to a set of rules and the
market keeps auctioning to facilitate
trade and discover price. And that whole
study of how that mechanism works is
called market microstructure. It's
basically the field that looks at the
rules and the mechanics of trading and
what those rules actually mean for how
prices move. We're going to rely on it
throughout this video because it's where
most of the proper answers come from
about how markets work. And the basic
building block of all of this mechanism
are orders. Now, an order is really just
an intention to buy or sell a certain
quantity of an asset. Right? As simple
as that. But there are two main order
types that you need to understand. And
those are market orders and limit
orders. A market order is about
immediacy. You're saying, "I want to buy
or sell right now at whatever price I
can get." So, if I send a market buy
order, I'll buy from the best available
sellers immediately. If I send a market
sell, I'll sell to the best available
buyers immediately. So, immediate
execution is the priority for a market
order, not what price I get filled at.
But a limit order is different. With a
limit order, you're basically saying,
I'm willing to trade, but only at this
price or better. So a buy limit is the
highest price you're willing to pay and
a sell limit is the lowest price you're
willing to accept. And if nobody can
trade with you on those terms yet, then
the order just sits there in the book.
And this is what people refer to as a
resting order. It's basically parked in
the market waiting to maybe be matched
with someone if someone comes along at
some point in time. So straight away
there's an important trade-off that
takes place here because market orders
prioritize execution but you give up
control over the exact price that you're
going to get. Whereas limit orders
prioritize price control but you give up
the certainty of execution. You know if
the market never reaches the price that
you set for your limit order then you
won't get filled. There'll be no trade.
Even if it touches that price briefly
but there are other orders ahead of
yours in the queue then you still might
not get filled. So there's no guarantee
that you're going to execute a trade if
you're using a limit order. But then if
we think about market orders, if we're
saying get me in this trade now at
whatever price I can get, then that
might mean we have to deal with
slippage. If the market's thin or moving
quickly, the price you actually end up
trading at can be very different to the
price that you saw on screen when you
click the button to enter the trade. So
even though the market order has done
what you wanted, which is get me into
this trade right now, it's not always
going to be at the price that you would
have agreed to if you knew what the
price was ahead of time. So now with
those two order types in mind, let's
take a look at how a trade actually
happens. So a transaction can only
happen when a buyer and a seller are
able to agree on a price. Until that
happens, you don't have a trade. You
just have interest sitting there in the
market. So, if I've got a buy limit at
99 and you've got a sell limit at 101,
nothing's going to happen. We've both
expressed a willingness to trade, but
our prices don't line up. So, we won't
do business with each other. But the
moment that somebody sends an order that
can transact with one of those resting
orders, business will get done. So, with
that in mind, we can think about things
this way. The market is made up of
passive and aggressive activity. A
passive order doesn't immediately trade.
it rests in the market and waits to be
hit or lifted by somebody else. So, a
buy order is passive if it's sitting
below the best available ask. And a sell
order is passive if it's sitting above
the best available bid. They're quoting
a price but not taking what's already
there. But an aggressive order is
different because it doesn't wait. It
crosses the spread and starts matching
with the opposite side straight away.
So, a buy order is aggressive if it's
willing to trade with the best available
asks right now. And a sell order is
aggressive if it's willing to trade for
the best available bids right now. And
that is the core mechanism of price
movement. Aggressive orders take up
resting liquidity. And if all of the
resting liquidity at the best price gets
eaten up, the market has to transact at
the next price level along. And that is
how price moves. And this is why that
sort of common expression of there being
more buyers than sellers in the market
just tends to get people confused and
doesn't really explain the situation
properly because every completed trade
still has both sides of the transaction.
Someone bought and someone sold equal
amounts. The real question is which side
was more aggressive and how much
liquidity was available on the other
side to absorb that aggression. you
know, price changes because the
available liquidity at one particular
price level got completely taken up and
the auction had to move somewhere else
to find more liquidity. And that's
something I'm going to show you with a
demonstration in just a moment. But
also, I want to talk about something
that I always see getting
oversimplified, which is limit orders.
You know, the usual thing that people
say is that limit orders are passive and
market orders are aggressive. And that's
often the case, but it isn't always the
case because a limit order just
specifies the worst price you're willing
to accept. It doesn't automatically mean
that the order has to wait, that it's a
resting order. Because if I send a buy
limit order above the current best ask,
that order can trade immediately with
the available sellers up to my limit
price. So, the limit order has crossed
the spread. We call that a marketable
limit order. It's behaving aggressively
in that moment. And it's the same thing
the other way round as well. A sell
limit placed below the current best bid
can immediately trade with available
buyers. So not every limit order becomes
a resting order. Some rest, meaning they
wait. Some cross, meaning they transact
straight away, and some cross partially,
meaning they transact with what they
can, and then the rest of it that hasn't
got filled, will rest in the book. It
will be a resting order. So, if someone
submits an order that can buy from the
best available sellers or sell to the
best available buyers, a transaction
will occur, whether it's a limit order
or a market order. That's what creates a
print in the market. That's what updates
the last traded price. And by the way,
it's important that you understand the
last traded price. This is the price
that you're usually going to see on your
price chart, and it's basically where
the last transaction took place. It's
not some sort of market consensus about
what the true value of the asset is.
It's simply the most recent price where
a buyer and a seller did business. So
that's what you're seeing on your price
chart. And it's also not necessarily the
price that you can trade at right now.
At any moments in time, the market has
two live prices. One for people who want
to sell right now and one for people who
want to buy right now. Those are the
bids and the ask. The best current
quotes on each side of the book. So the
last traded price, what you're seeing on
your price chart, tells you where
business last happened. and the bids and
the asks tell you where the next
business could happen. Okay, so
hopefully you've been able to follow
along with all of that, but I do know
that we've gone through quite a bit
already. So, let me show you all of this
with a demonstration to make it easier
to understand. Okay, so what you can see
on screen here is just a simple
simulator that I created to help you
sort of understand these concepts. So,
on the left hand side, you can see the
candlestick chart and on the right is a
simplified bid and ask ladder.
Basically, a stripped down version of
the order book. So first if I add a
bunch of resting limit orders, let's see
what happens. Okay, so I'll add bid
liquidity. And you can see quantity
building up on the bid side, but you can
see that price isn't moving based on
that. Why? Because I've added liquidity.
I haven't taken any. I've not consumed
any. So these are passive orders
entering the market. And same thing if I
add ask liquidity. I've added
willingness to sell, but I haven't
forced a transaction yet. So now what if
I press the button to do a market buy
for 50. Watch what happens. So the order
is immediately going to go into the ask
side and start matching with the best
available sellers. So that's aggressive
flow taking liquidity from the market.
So let's think about what happens when
that order hits the market. So first of
all, it's going to transact against the
lowest priced limit orders. Okay? So if
there's enough quantity at that level
for me to transact against, then that
would be the end of it. My orders
filled. I'm happy, I move on. But if my
market order was for a higher quantity
than what was available at that first
price, it would then have to transact at
the next price where there's more
liquidity. And so on and so on until my
order is fully filled. So if there's
enough liquidity at the best ask, then a
transaction takes place, but price will
barely move. But the more liquidity I
need, the more price will need to move
up. And this is sometimes known as bookw
walking because if a marketable order is
bigger than the available liquidity at
the best price, it will keep trading at
the next level, the next, the next until
it's either filled or its limit price
stops it. And that's what people mean
when they say that an order walked the
book. So that example was obviously with
a market order, but now let's look at an
aggressive limit order. So remember, a
limit order is usually thought of as
being passive, but actually a marketable
limit order can be aggressive and
transact straight away. So if instead of
a market orders to buy, I place a limit
order to buy above the current best ask.
Let's see what happens. So you can see
it trades immediately with the available
asks up to my limit. In other words, it
crosses the book and if I ask for more
than what's available at the best ask,
it keeps trading into higher and higher
ask levels until either I've been fully
filled, my order's complete, or my limit
price stops me from going any further.
anything left over is going to rest in
the book as a resting limit order at
that price. And obviously, we can do
exactly the same with sell orders as
well. And exactly the same mechanisms
will take place just in the opposite
direction. But keep in mind what I'm
demonstrating here is very simplified
because it's just one order being placed
at a time in a static simulator. In the
real markets, there'll be many orders
from many different market participants
being placed all the time in either
direction of the book. So now that you
hopefully understand the basic mechanics
of all of this, let's take a closer look
at the order book. The limit order book
is just the organized list of resting
buy and sell orders. It can be displayed
in a bunch of different ways. It can be
referred to as different things like the
depth of market or the DOM, the ladder,
the order book, but the basics of it are
usually the same. The bid side contains
the buy orders. The ask side, sometimes
also called the offer side, contains the
sell orders. The highest bid is the best
bid because that's the highest price
somebody's currently willing to pay. And
the lowest ask is the best ask because
that's the lowest price somebody is
currently willing to sell at. And the
gap between those two prices is the
spread. So this is what I referred to
earlier when I said there are two live
prices. There's a current best buyer and
a current best seller. And the price
chart isn't going to necessarily show
you that negotiation. It's showing the
prices that transactions actually
happened at. Now, in most order-driven
markets, but not necessarily all, some
different exchanges have different rules
about this, the book will normally be
organized by price, time, priority. So,
that means the better price obviously
goes first, but then if multiple orders
are placed at the same exact price,
they're prioritized based on what time
the orders were placed. So, whoever gets
there soonest will get filled first. And
this creates a queue. But, like I said,
different exchanges might have slightly
different rules. They do sometimes have
different rules about this, but you
don't need to worry about that for now.
Basically, it means that when an
aggressive order comes into the market,
it trades against the specific resting
orders at the best available prices in
the order of the priority queue. So,
what this actually means in practical
terms is that you might place a limit
order at a particular price and even if
the market reaches that price, you still
might not get filled if there are people
ahead of you in the queue who get filled
first and then there are no more
transactions to be made. So your place
in the queue determines when you're
going to get filled if price is at that
level. Okay. So getting back to the
order book here, we can see that at each
price level, there's a quantity. So
that's the quantity that's currently
available. We can sort of think of this
like advertising in the markets. So this
is how much interest is being expressed
at each price level. But obviously that
doesn't mean how many transactions are
actually going to take place. In the
real markets, orders can be added to or
removed from the book, which is
sometimes known as pulling and stacking.
And this can actually have an influence
on the behavior in the markets, which is
something we'll discuss a bit later.
Now, with most charting platforms, you
can actually add this information to the
order book. But depending on how you're
trading, that might or might not be
relevant for you. So, with that in mind,
once a price level gets cleared out when
the liquidity is taken, then there are
one of two things that could happen. New
liquidity could refill the area, orders
being added, which shows the market is
resilient around the area. Or it might
be that the market keeps moving on to
new prices because there isn't much
replenishment. And that difference is
going to tell you a lot about the
dynamics in the market at that time
because it's the difference between a
move meeting real support or resistance
or a move where the market was already
empty in that area and just kept going.
And again, we'll discuss all of that a
bit later. Now, if you're new to all of
this, the obvious next question is going
to be where do I actually see any of
this? So access to the order book is
going to differ for different markets,
different exchanges. And for example,
with Forex, you don't really have a
reliable order book because it's not one
centralized exchange. You could look at
the futures market for currencies, but
it's not going to be showing you the
whole market. So it's not going to be as
reliable as some other markets. Like for
example, with futures, crypto, stocks,
bonds, you can get access to this sort
of information and it's going to be a
lot more reliable. And remember, like I
said earlier, sometimes this is going to
be known as the DOM or depth of market,
sometimes the order book. So, whatever
charting platform you're using, you
might have to look under a few different
terms to be able to find it. But
remember, the order book is the
pre-trade information. It's showing you
quoted liquidity, so the orders that are
waiting to trade. And then, if you want
to see the actual transactions that took
place, then you need to see the
post-trade information. And this is what
you see within your candlestick charts.
But if you want a more detailed view,
you could also use the footprint chart.
So the footprint chart is showing you
the quantity that was actually
transacted at different prices and
whether it was executed on the bid or
ask side of the book. And this is
important information because it allows
you to see which side was being
aggressive to make the transactions
happen. Because even though a trade
needs both a buyer and a seller, you
remember from the demonstration that
price movements are as a result of the
aggressive side of the trade. So this
sort of information can be useful and if
you want to see this, if you want to see
the footprint charts and the DOM, I'd
recommend using a more specialized
platform. I know most people use
Training View. I do think they're
offering like footprint charts these
days, but my personal favorite is Sierra
Chart where you can get the footprint
chart, the DOM, and many other detailed
charting tools. No, I'm not sponsored or
anything. It's just the one that I
recommend. It is a bit tricky to get
your head around at first. There's a lot
of customization you can do. It's a bit
more complex than the retail friendly
platforms, but if you spend some time
messing around with it, you will start
to figure it out. It doesn't take that
long. Don't be daunted by it. And if you
do want a detailed guide on Sierra
Chart, how it works, how to set it up,
how to customize it, just let me know in
the comments. I'll be happy to do that.
There are other interesting platforms as
well, like Book Map and things like
that, but those can get a bit more
complex and probably a bit unnecessary
for most traders unless you really know
what you're doing. But listen, I do have
to say that although it's really useful
to see the markets broken down in that
way with a footprint chart, the order
book and all those complex tools, you
can achieve a lot with just a
candlestick chart as long as you know
how to interpret the context correctly
and how to derive that sort of
information from the sort of activity
you're seeing on the candlestick chart.
You know, a lot of people will tell you
that a candlestick chart is just for
retail traders and the more complex
charts are the professional ways to do
things, but honestly, that's really not
true. There are pros and cons of both,
but a genuinely skilled trader will be
able to succeed using either. And
candlestick charts can reveal a lot more
than most people realize. You just need
to know how to do it correctly. And
again, like I mentioned earlier, if you
want to start learning how to approach
the markets in a more logical way and to
learn how I trade, to learn how to
interpret the context correctly, then
just sign up for the free training
that's linked down below. So the DOM,
the depth of market, shows what's
resting in the market. The tape or the
footprint chart show what's actually
traded and then heat map tools like
bookmap sort of visualizes how quoted
liquidity appears, disappears, gets
pulled, and refills over time, usually
alongside the executions that went
through. By the way, order flow is not
some special institutional trading
secret. Whenever trading YouTubers
suggest that it is, then it's just
marketing. They're just trying to
elevate themselves because they know
that order flow looks more complex and
they can make you believe that anyone
using a candlestick chart is just a
little retail peasant. But at the end of
the day, it's just an information
source. It doesn't automatically give
you better skills. None of these tools
are going to magically show you how to
trade. They're just different ways of
displaying the same underlying process.
I've been doing this for over two
decades and I understand order flow very
well. But I still spend most of my time
on the price chart and I can trade just
as well with just that. Okay. All right.
Now, just before we move on to discuss
some of the more interesting
implications of everything that we've
gone through so far, we first need to
clear up one of the biggest
misconceptions in trading. Market
makers. There's this sort of cartoonish
conspiracy theory that retail traders
are brainwashed with that market makers
are out there stalking your stops and
plotting their next move against retail
traders manipulating price just to hurt
the little guy. And that's usually the
picture people have in mind when they
talk about market manipulation and it
makes you feel better about your bad
decisions because there's someone else
to blame. But really, it's just trading
educators using marketing psychology by
creating an us versus them narrative
that helps sell their illogical trading
approach by making it sound more legit
than it is. But that's not the reality.
The reality is actually a lot more
mechanical than that and a lot more
useful to understand than that story
that gets perpetuated. So market makers
and other liquidity providers are there
to quote bids and offers, provide
liquidity, manage their inventory, earn
the spread when they can, and avoid
getting run over by directional flow.
Now, they're not there as a charity.
Obviously, they want to make money, but
the way they typically do that is by
managing liquidity and risk, and not so
much by directional plays in the market,
and definitely not by trying to
personally hunt down your one lot
stop-loss. Now, can liquidity providers
benefit when price moves into obvious
stop areas? Of course. Can they step
back when conditions get choppy? Yes.
Can they widen spreads, reduce size or
pull liquidity around major economic
releases and other news? Absolutely. You
know, around things like inflation data,
payrolls, central bank decisions, one of
the reasons that price can absolutely
rip is not just because new information
has hit the market. It's also that the
book is often going to be much thinner
during those moments because liquidity
providers don't necessarily want to
stand there passively offering size into
a violent repricing event. So they pull
liquidity. So the book thins out,
spreads widen, depth deteriorates, and
that means that even a fairly normal
burst of aggressive flow can have a much
bigger effect on price than it normally
would because there just isn't enough
liquidity there to absorb it. But then
obviously when it is a major economic
data release or other major news event
then it's going to be a lot of volume
meaning market orders coming to the
market. So you have a combination of
liquidity being pulled and a lot of
market orders hitting the book at the
same time. So prices obviously need to
accelerate to fill the orders to find
that liquidity. And also while we're on
the topic of manipulation, it's also
worth knowing that some large market
participants legitimately hide their
orders as well. And it's not to
manipulate you, but it's because they
don't want to telegraph their intent to
the rest of the market. So there are
iceberg orders, for example, where only
a small part of the true size of the
position is shown on the book. And then
when that gets hit, they'll just keep
refilling that visible part in the book
until their full position gets filled.
So let's take a look at a demonstration
of that. So we can see some liquidity
here at the next price in the book. But
as I transact against it, you can see
that it keeps getting refilled because
if that participant put their full order
straight into the book, the market would
know there's a lot of liquidity there, a
big position that needs to get filled.
And then they'd know they're protected
from any moves higher. So that means
they can frontr run it and sell market
orders just before the price gets there,
which means the big order is less likely
to get filled. They might not get the
price that they want. So, they're going
to disguise it by using an iceberg where
they'll just keep refilling the book
each time that gets hit. And listen,
there's a lot more that we could discuss
about that type of thing as well. But
for now, let's just get back to the
foundations. So, hopefully by this
point, you're starting to understand why
it is that some markets see a lot of
price movement and some don't see much
at all, or even why one particular
market can move a lot at certain times
of the day or on certain days and then
not much on other times of the day or
other days. So if there's a lot of
resting liquidity close to the current
price, then a fair amount of aggressive
buying or selling can be absorbed
without the price having to move much.
In that case, the book is deep. It can
soak up flow. But if there isn't so much
liquidity or if the liquidity gets
pulled away, then the book is thin and
even a relatively modest surge of
aggressive flow can produce a
surprisingly large price move. And then
there are sometimes gaps in the quizzity
at certain prices and those are
sometimes known as air pockets. So if a
section of the book is relatively empty,
there's nothing for an order to transact
against, then the price is just going to
move through those areas quite quickly.
So we can think of it then that you
could have the same level of aggression
hitting a market, but with very
different conditions in the order book,
you're going to have very different
price outcomes. So let's go back to the
simulator so we can make all of this
clear. So if I use the same market buy
size in a deep book, then you can see
what happens. And then in a thin book,
you can see completely different
behavior. In the deep book, the same
order barely even nudges the price
because there's plenty of liquidity
sitting there that can absorb that
order. But in a thin book, that exact
same order suddenly looks very dramatic
in the price move because there isn't
much to trade against there. So price
has to move to find that liquidity. So
this should give you a really important
insight. If we get a dramatic price move
in the market, we can't automatically
assume that it means that that side of
the market was really strong. The
question should always be strong
relative to what liquidity because
sometimes the move isn't showing
overwhelming buying or selling pressure.
Sometimes it's just showing us that the
market at that time was thin as hell.
And that's the thing that you need to
keep in mind. Prices move based on
imbalances between volume and liquidity.
The bigger the move, the bigger the
imbalance was. But that level of
imbalance is created by two sides, not
just one. It's not just about the level
of market orders. It's also about the
level of liquidity. So, let's go a bit
deeper here because this is where a lot
of traders really miss the point. And
this is the basis of a lot of really
illogical trading approaches. And
honestly, the vast majority of
strategies and approaches that are
taught throughout the trading education
industry fall into that category. Just
completely illogical, even delusional.
No predictive power, just picking up on
meaningless visuals that appear on a
price chart without really understanding
the context. So, here's the thing. When
we see a strong trend taking place, it's
not just price moving in one direction
really quickly. like visually that's
what we see happening on the price chart
but what's really happening underneath
that could be a whole range of different
things and each of those are going to
completely change the way we perceive
that situation. So on one hand we have
the imbalance that's happening that's
causing that price move because of
aggressive buying or selling continuing
to hit the market and taking all the
liquidity at each price level. Okay,
straightforward now that you understand
how orders happen, how price moves. Now,
that might be because there's a huge
amount of market orders, or it could be
that it's just a regular amount of
market orders that are hitting a thin
book. But then there's also how well
supported that move is. So, if the
market pulls back, are there resting
orders on the other side that can absorb
that and support the move or is it
unsupported? Meaning any pullbacks can
be equally as rapid. So, that might be
the case when the move is happening
because liquidity has been pulled. It's
a thin book. It looks exciting on a
price chart like this big breakout's
happening or something like that. But
underneath that, there might not
actually be that much real participation
behind the move. But on the other hand,
you might have a situation where the
market rips higher and then on every
small dip, every small pullback, it
keeps finding more buyers there willing
to absorb the selling and support that
move. That's a very different situation
from a market that's ripping higher just
because liquidity is temporarily thinned
out. Very different situations. on the
chart, they'll both look like strong
bullish moves, but underneath behind the
scenes, they're not the same thing at
all. So, let me show you a demonstration
so you understand what I mean with this.
Okay, so first we're going to load a
thin book and hit it with a big market
buy. So, you can see just how easily
price jumps up. It looks really
impressive on the candle chart. But now,
watch what happens if selling comes in
afterwards and there isn't much real
support behind that move. We can see
that the move can unwind just as
quickly. Just as quickly as it got up
there, it can reverse and correct that
move. I'm sure you've seen many
situations like this before because it
wasn't really built on much. It was just
going into this sort of empty space. But
now, let's compare that to a market
where, you know, we have the market
orders come in that moves price up, but
then on the pullback, you can see
liquidity on the bid side building and
absorbing that selling. So, that's a
much healthier move. This is a move
that's being held together rather than
just floating into empty space. And also
something else to keep in mind is that
if you don't have a thin book and you
still manage to achieve a big price move
like that, then everyone else is going
to be seeing that as well. And people
will start pulling liquidity or you know
jumping on board as well and you get
this sort of hering effect, a synchrony
effect in the market that leads to that
move happening even quicker sometimes
beyond that point. There are plenty of
things that can happen, lots of
different scenarios that can take place.
And listen, this is actually one of the
biggest practical insights, and this is
something I really hope you're going to
take away with you from this video, that
when you're looking at a price chart and
you're seeing momentum, don't just ask
how fast that momentum is, how fast that
price move is. Ask what kind of move it
is. Is it initiative action with real
follow through? Is it finding support on
the pullbacks? Is it being accepted at
the new prices? or is it a thin unstable
sprint into an empty space that's about
to reverse and snap back? Okay, so now I
want to zoom out a little bit and
briefly discuss something called auction
market theory. So obviously
understanding how the order book works
helps us to understand how price moves
can happen. But the market isn't just a
sequence of random little transactions
happening. There's also a broader
auction process taking place. And so the
basic idea is that obviously the markets
are continuously auctioning higher and
lower to find prices where trades can
best be facilitated. So price advertises
opportunity. Time regulates it and
volume measures how successful the
auction was at that price. So if a price
attracts time and volume, it's being
accepted. If price trades somewhere just
briefly and then gets driven away, it's
being rejected. And I think that's a
really useful way to think about things
in the markets even on just a basic
level. It gives you a much more
meaningful way to assess things like
ranges, breakouts, and reversals. Let's
think about a range for example. If we
think about it from a simple point of
view, it's just the market spending time
in an area where both sides are
reasonably willing to do business. So
aggressive buying gets absorbed,
aggressive selling gets absorbed and
neither side is doing enough to force
lasting acceptance in a new price area.
So price rotates, it explores, it goes a
bit too high, then a bit too low, it
comes back, it goes again. The market is
trying to facilitate trade. So when that
happens, we can think of this as being a
balanced area where price is being
accepted. People are willing to trade
there. And then you have concepts like
the point of control or useful tools
like market profile, volume profile,
VWAP. Now, we're not going to be
discussing all of those things in this
video, but you can let me know in the
comments if you want me to cover them in
a future video. It's something that we
do use at Duomo, order flow, auction
market theory, things like that to
support what we do with the Duo method,
but it's not a core part of it. Most of
our trading relies on the Duomo market
theory as our basis rather than auction
market theory. But these are all still
things that are taught inside our
program. It's still things that we do
use and it it's relevant. It's useful
and auction market theory is especially
relevant to the topic that we're
discussing today, which is why I brought
it up. But anyway, bringing all of this
back to your trading. This is one of the
big things that you need to assess when
you're analyzing the context in the
markets. You need to be thinking about
this, not just thinking, oh, price is
moving sideways, but what that sideways
activity is actually saying about
acceptance, participation, and where
trades can best be facilitated right
now. And then we can apply the same way
of thinking to things like breakouts as
well. Like a breakout is not just price
moving through a significant level.
That's just the visual event. That's
what you're seeing on the price chart.
But the more important question is
whether the market can keep doing
business beyond that point. In other
words, is the new price area going to be
accepted or is it just probed briefly
and then rejected? So let's have a look
at that on the simulator. Okay, so I've
set up a range in the simulator and
we're going to see a breakout through
one side of that. Now in this first
example, once we get that breakout,
you're going to see that the buying
continues and the market starts holding
itself above the previous area. So
business is being done at the new
prices. That's a sign of initiative
action and acceptance at new prices,
right? So that's a healthy breakout. Now
in the second example, we're going to
push through in exactly the same kind of
way, the same level, same sort of
breakout, but this time you can see
price move quickly back into the range.
So the move wasn't supported. That's
rejection or responsive action that's
taking place. So, the initial breakout
looks the same visually at first glance,
but there's a completely different thing
going on behind the scenes. And this is
exactly why when traders just memorize
breakout setups and breakout patterns,
it's such an unreliable way of trading.
Because two charts could seem like they
look almost identical at the moment of
the breakout, but the context and the
quality of the auction can be completely
different. And this is why traders often
complain about false breakouts because
they're basing things just on what's
happened visually in that moment as it's
breaking out rather than thinking fully
about the context and understanding if
enough activity is actually going to
happen to sustain that move, if prices
will be accepted, if business will be
done at those new price levels. And this
is why when we're analyzing the context
in the market, we don't just ask where
is price going or where has price gone,
but also how well has it got there or
how well is it getting there? What clues
are there that tell us about what's
really going on in the market other than
just how that price move looks? You
know, proper analysis should be more of
an investigation, not just a game of
spotting things on the chart. Now, since
we talked about false breakouts, we
should also talk about stop runs because
these are the moments where traders are
convinced that their stops got hunted,
which is something I briefly mentioned
earlier when we were talking about
market makers. But let's actually dig
into what happens in the market. So,
first of all, now that you understand
how price moves in the markets,
hopefully you should also understand
something else really important that
your orders in the market are really
inconsequential.
Most of the passive liquidity and the
aggressive marketable orders are coming
from the big participants in the market.
So it's big market participants that are
causing price moves that are dictating
the price moves. If you think about like
big mutual funds, pension funds and so
on, your small orders are a drop in the
ocean. They're inconsequential.
No one is hunting your stop personally.
But stop losses are an important part of
all of this. But first, you need to
understand what a stop order actually
is. So, it's an order that only becomes
active once a certain price is reached.
So, let's say, for example, that right
now you've got a short trade that's
open. And so, you've got a stop-loss
that's going to be a buy stop above the
current price to protect yourself if
price reverses against you. Now, that's
essentially waiting in the background
until price reaches it and triggers it.
And once price gets there and triggers
it, the stop activates. Now, that sounds
a lot like a limit order, but it's not
because once it's activated, it then
becomes a market order and starts trying
to get filled at the best available
prices. Because if you have a stop-loss,
you want to make sure that once it's
triggered, you're taken out of the
position. Whereas, if it was a limit
order, there's no guarantee of that. But
if it executes as a market order, it
prioritizes immediate execution. So, you
get out of the trade. But think about
what that actually means. So, if these
are market orders rather than limit
orders, it means that if we break above
a high, for example, and trigger a bunch
of buy stops, those stops become market
orders, which means that they're going
to be contributing aggressive buying. If
we break below a low and trigger sell
stops, they're going to become
aggressive selling. So, they could
influence the price to move further in
that direction as the orders get filled.
So, already price has moved through that
level. Then as the stops are triggered,
it's going to accelerate that move
further or add to it. And that is what
happens when there's a stop run. So
price moves into an area where a lot of
stop orders are likely to be triggered
or where traders are likely to be forced
into action one way or another. And when
all of those orders are triggered, it
brings a lot of aggressive action to the
market that leads to price continuing,
sometimes even accelerating in that
direction. But just like we discussed
with a breakout, it's what happens next
that's important. Because if those stops
get triggered and then the market keeps
doing business at the new prices, fine,
the move may continue because those new
prices are being accepted. But if the
stops get triggered and then no new
business is done at those new levels,
price might just fall back straight into
the old area that it was in. So let's
have a look at that on the simulator.
Okay, so we're going to push the price
into an obvious stop area just above the
range and watch what happens. So we
burst through, we accelerate as those
stops are triggered. But now in this
version, watch what happens next where
the market starts accepting those higher
prices and we start to move a bit
further and further up. It might even
consolidate in some situations up there.
But then we can look at this version
here where price rips through, the stops
are triggered, and then the whole thing
just melts back into the range. So
that's the difference between a breakout
with acceptance and a stop run that
triggered some activity for a short
amount of time and then reversed. So a
stop run could be something temporary
like a false breakout or it might be a
lasting change in the direction of the
market and that change might be
initially triggered by the stop run or
the stop run might just be collateral
damage of a price move that was going to
happen anyway just helping to accelerate
it. Now let me make something absolutely
clear. You might be watching this and
thinking, "Oh, great. So, now I need
like 17 screens and a chart setup that
looks like a nuclear submarine control
panel." You don't. You don't need
perfect X-ray vision of the market to be
able to start thinking more
intelligently about what's likely going
on. Yes, if you have footprint charts,
the DOM, heat maps, all of that sort of
stuff, lovely, it can help. But even
without seeing all of those details,
just by learning to interpret context
correctly on a price chart, you'll be
able to deduce what's likely going on.
The problem is that most traders don't
do that. They don't go anywhere near to
doing that. They just look at the most
recent price moves and try to assume
something from that. And that means that
they miss all of the clues that the
markets left behind up until that point.
and all of those clues. It's like you
can connect the dots and make pretty
solid assumptions about the activity in
the markets if you understand what
you're looking at. So yes, all the stuff
that we've been discussing will be very
helpful for you. It will still work even
if you don't choose to use any of the
complex charting. As I said earlier, I
don't most of the time, like 95% of the
time, I don't use the orderflow
charting. And yes, it will still work
for you even if you're trading forex
where you don't have as much
transparency about what's going on
behind the scenes. Understanding this
stuff is still going to help you to
analyze the markets better. The most
important thing is that if you're just
using a trading approach where you're
basically spotting, plotting, and
labeling things on a chart rather than
actively trying to investigate and
interpret what's really going on to
understand the context, you need to
change what you're doing. If you're
following a predefined strategy that you
can just apply whenever you see what
looks like a valid setup, you need to
change what you're doing. Listen, things
don't need to be overly complicated. But
you also shouldn't be defaulting to
whatever just sounds simple and easiest
to learn really quickly because those
things usually don't work. And hopefully
you're starting to see why. Because once
you start understanding how the market
really functions, it's easy already to
find the clear flaws in most trading
approaches that everyone learns. You
know, there's so much information that
we can pick up on from each unique
situation in the markets that helps us
to make more accurate forecasts and make
the right decisions to take better
trades. And if you're only focusing on
what looks similar in each situation
because you're following some strategy
or looking for setups or patterns or
whatever, you're automatically ignoring
what's different. And each situation in
the markets is unique. Yes, there are
similarities from time to time. There
are a lot of differences as well. And
those differences matter just as much as
the similarities. But strategy, setups,
things like that, just focus on what's
similar. Ignore what's different. And
that's a recipe for disaster. Now, even
though this was actually quite a long
video, and I'm losing my voice now
because of that, there's still so much
we could talk about and many other
advanced things as well that we could
get into, especially things that matter
more to the institutional side of this.
things like Q position, the different
costs of either providing or taking
liquidity, inventory risk for liquidity
providers, iceberg orders, hidden
liquidity, order splitting, all of these
kinds of things. But all of these things
are really useful to understand, but
they're not something that you
absolutely have to know right now. So,
what we discussed in this video, that's
the important stuff for now. But if you
do want us to get into more of the
advanced stuff or just go deeper into
this topic, let me know in the comments
section. And also do me a big favor and
hit the like button if you want more
videos like this one because they take a
lot longer to put together. They burn
out my voice. So I don't want to spend
time on them if no one's interested,
even though I think they should be.
These are important topics. So hit the
like button and let me know. But for
now, the important thing is that you
understand the mechanisms that take
place in the markets. That should be
foundational knowledge for every trader,
but surprisingly for most traders, it's
not. And it really shows. So, if you've
understood the things that we've gone
through, even if you have to rewatch it
a few times to get your head around
certain things, you're already way ahead
of most traders out there who are just
on a path to failure. So, next time
you're at the charts, don't just take
price moves at face value. Think about
what possible things may have had to
happen for that move to occur and then
see what clues there are to help you
confirm which of those options it likely
was. Ask whether a move is supported or
not, whether pullbacks are finding real
participation or not, whether the market
is accepting new prices or rejecting
them, and ask what the context is
telling you about the real activity
taking place. Because that really is why
context matters so much. It ties the
whole thing together. Without context,
even order flow becomes just a bunch of
disconnected observations. But with
context, you can start making
intelligent assumptions about what the
market is likely doing. even when you
can't see every single piece of
information directly. And that's a
massive part of what we focus on at
Duomo. And it's exactly what the free
training that's linked down below will
help you to start developing properly.
Because it's a skill, it takes time, but
when you learn how to do it, the results
that you can achieve will make all of
the effort completely worthwhile. Thanks
for watching. See you soon.